A Guide to the Reid Stanger Fulton Papers, 1900-1976
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Reid Stanger Fulton Papers, 1900-1976
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1978-010
0.2 cu. ft. 1 box
Correspondence, legal papers, and printed materials of Reid Stanger Fulton, economics instructor, avid book collector, and owner of Graham mansion at Max Meadows, Virginia.
Fulton, Reid Stanger, 1886-c.1984
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Reid Stanger Fulton Papers were acquired by Special Collections prior to 1979.
Biographical Note
Reid Stanger Fulton, the son of Samuel M. and Margret E. Fulton, was born in Grayson County, Virginia on September 4, 1886. After graduating from the Dublin Institute (Pulaski County, Virginia), Fulton attended the University of Virginia, then earned bachelor's and master's degrees at the University of Michigan. He served as a high school principal for a year, taught at Culver Military Institute for a year and served as an instructor in the University of Michigan's School of Oratory. In 1918, he became director of Drake University's School of Commerce. He was still teaching at Drake as late as 1935, but by 1954 was serving as an instructor of economics at City College of New York.
In 1943, Fulton purchased the Graham mansion at Max Meadows, Virginia. He continued to teach at City College of New York until retiring in the late 1950s, when he retired to the mansion. Here, he housed his massive book collection and derived an income from the sale of timber. Fulton sold the mansion to Dr. James L. Chitwood in 1974 but retained residency there for the remainder of his life.
Reid Stanger Fulton died at Max Meadows in September 1979 and is buried in the Fulton Family Cemetery at Independence (Grayson County), Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Reid Stanger Fulton, economics instructor, avid book collector, and owner of the Graham mansion (Max Meadows, Virginia). Included are several letters and legal agreements, relating largely to Fulton's Wythe County, Virginia property. The collection also includes a small collection of stock certificates, probably gathered by Fulton in the course of his book-collecting. A small set of newspaper clippings within the collection provides information on both Fulton and the Graham mansion, while Fulton's career as a college instructor is represented in several class records and a 1958 economics examination. Also included are two 1922 issues of Journal of Business, featuring articles written by Fulton. A folder of typescript pieces includes an essay by Fulton titled "Is There a Paucity of Political Leadership," a short story titled "It Is Our Turn," signed "M.S. C.," an anonymous commencement address, and what appear to be course lecture notes. A folder of general materials completes the collection and includes a 1923 passport for Katherine Gourley (born 1853 in Ireland). Like the stock certificates, the passport probably has no personal connection to Fulton but was instead likely acquired by him in the course of collecting. The folder also includes two receipts issued to Fulton for the purchase of textbooks, some 1950s political/religious circular letters, and a land-use map for Fulton's Wythe County property.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by document type.
Index Terms
Local Subjects:
Local/Regional History
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1951-1953. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Legal agreements, 1943-1959. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Stock certificates, 1900-1921, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Alaska British Columbia Metals Company (interim), n.d., [2 items]
  - Alaska British cvolumbia Metals Company, [1921]., [2 items]
  - Cuban Central Railway Company, 1900., [2 items]
  - Panama Tramways Company, 1914., [4 items]
- Newspaper clippings, 1921-1976. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Drake University class record, 1935. (Box-folder 1-5)
- City College class records, 1954-1956. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Economics examination, 1958. (Box-folder 1-7)
- Journal of Business, 1922., [2 items] (Box-folder 1-8)
- Writings, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
- General materials, 1923-1952, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)